The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series VI. Exhibitions, 1938-1969
  - Paintings by Italian Children[MoMA Exh. #571, February 16-March 20, 1955], November 1954-April 1955; Correspondence, checklist, reviews, wall text, MoMA press release (Box 38, Folder VI.86)
  - Developing Creativeness In Children[MoMA Exh. #575, March 15-April 17, 1955], Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 38, Folder VI.87)
  - Developing Creativeness In Children[MoMA Exh. #575, March 15-April 17, 1955], Photoreproductions of panels, mounted, with pin marks. These may have been with materials returned to Arlette Buchman from a 1995 loan exhibition in Japan (see also folder VIII.A.50). (Box 39, Folder VI.88)
  - Developing Creativeness In Children[MoMA Exh. #575, March 15-April 17, 1955], Photographs of exhibition panels: color and b/w glass-mounted slides (Box 39, Folder VI.89)
  - Developing Creativeness In Children[MoMA Exh. #575, March 15-April 17, 1955], From a traveling version of the exhibition: guide to installing the exhibition, including checklist of panels, installation photographs (Box 39, Folder VI.90)
  - Painting by Amateurs[MoMA Exh. #586, October 12-November 20, 1955], Exhibition subtitle was "14 students from classes of the People's Art Center." Photographs of objects in the exhibition and installation views, adult students working: b/w prints (Box 39, Folder VI.91)
  - Art Education for Every Child[MoMA Exh. #665, May 6-August 14, 1960], Exhibition held in conjunction with 18th annual meeting of National Committee on Art Education at MoMA (see also Series VIII.C). Installation views and photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 39, Folder VI.92)
  - Art Education for Every Child[MoMA Exh. #665, May 6-August 14, 1960], From original folder marked "xtra photos"; images of children making art, many with crop marks or other hand emendations: b/w prints (Box 39, Folder VI.93)
  - Art Education for Every Child[MoMA Exh. #665, May 6-August 14, 1960], 1960-1980, 1991; Includes wall labels, materials list, staff list, newspaper clippings. Material culled by Teachers College on People’s Art Center (Box 39, Folder VI.94)
  - Work from the Children's Art Carnival in India[MoMA Exh. #755, February 2-February 26, 1965], February 2, 1965; MoMA press release (Box 39, Folder VI.95)
  - Work from the Children's Art Carnival in India[MoMA Exh. #755, February 2-February 26, 1965], Installation views, wall labels: b/w prints, transparencies (Box 39, Folder VI.96)
  - The Kearsarge Art Group[MoMA Exh. #762, April 15-May 28, 1965], Installation views, photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints, color slides (Box 39, Folder VI.97)
  - Children's Art from the Hong Kong Schools[MoMA Exh. #759, March 9-April 3, 1965], Installation views, press photographs from Hong Kong government: b/w prints (Box 39, Folder VI.98)
  - Art Work by Children & Young People from the Classes of the Art Center[MoMA Exh. #767b, June 7-July 30, 1965], Installation views: mounted b/w prints (Box 40, Folder VI.99)
  - Art Work by Children & Young People from the Classes of the Art Center[MoMA Exh. #767b, June 7-July 30, 1965], Installation views (two sets): b/w prints, color transparencies (Box 40, Folder VI.100)
  - Art Work of Japanese Children[MoMA Exh. #783, December 15, 1965-February 19, 1966], Installation views: b/w prints (Box 40, Folder VI.101)
  - Work from Adult Classes[MoMA Exh. #793, March 16-April 29, 1966], March 1966; Installation views (two sets): b/w prints and negatives (Box 40, Folder VI.102)
  - Art Work from the Elementary and Secondary Schools of Egypt[March 27-April 29, 1967], Unnumbered exhibition in the Art Center; installation views and photographs of objects in the exhibition: b/w prints (Box 40, Folder VI.103)
  - Accent on 3D Expression, October 1967; Unnumbered People's Art Center exhibition; installation views: b/w prints (Box 40, Folder VI.104)
  - By Children and Young People 2 1/2 - 17 years[MoMA Exh. #875, November 18, 1968-January 11, 1969], Fall 1968; “Some statements on art education” prepared in connection with the exhibition by the Art Center: nine copies (Box 40, Folder VI.105)
  - Pioneering in Art Education[MoMA Exh. #908, October 30, 1969-January 30, 1970], Invitation; wall labels: transparencies and photocopies; installation views, from original box marked "Early Days": color slides (Box 40, Folder VI.106)
  - Pioneering in Art Education[MoMA Exh. #908, October 30, 1969-January 30, 1970], Images of D'Amico and MoMA programs: b/w prints, transparencies (Box 40, Folder VI.107)
- Series VII. MoMA Publications, 1941-1972
  The series includes documentation of MoMA publications both written and collaborated on by D'Amico, as well as others found in his files.
  Various MoMA publications, including How to Make Pottery and Ceramic Sculpture: 20 Graded Projects;How to Make Modern Jewelry; and How to Make Objects of Wood, originated as pamphlets created by, and based on work done by students at, the War Veterans' Art Center (see Series III.A).
  The series includes some visual materials once housed in MoMA's Photographic Archive, which had been placed there based on the earlier organization of documentation by material type rather than in context with items from similar sources.
  - MoMA Bulletins, clipping, 1941, 1943, 1946, undated; "Modern Art for Children: The Educational Project" (MoMA Bulletin, vol IX); "The arts in therapy” (MoMA Bulletin 3, vol X); "The Department of Industrial Design" (MoMA Bulletin, vol. XIV, fall 1946); "Educating Artistic Vision" (clipping mentioning D'Amico's book,Creative Teaching in Art) (Box 40, Folder VII.1)
  - Published information on art materials, 1943, undated; Includes "Making Your Own Art Materials" published by the Committee on Art in American Education and Society, with introduction by D'Amico (Box 40, Folder VII.2)
  - What is Modern Painting?, 1945; Educational Program copy; stamped "Do Not Take from People's Art Center" (Box 40, Folder VII.3)
  - How to Make Modern Jewelry(1 of 3), 1946; Photographs of objects used in the book. Label notes that "much of the material in the book was made in the Veterans' Art Center - World War II": mounted b/w prints removed from post album (Box 41, Folder VII.4)
  - How to Make Modern Jewelry(2 of 3), 1946; Photographs of objects used in the book. Label notes that "much of the material in the book was made in the Veterans' Art Center - World War II": mounted b/w prints removed from post album (Box 41, Folder VII.5)
  - How to Make Modern Jewelry(3 of 3), 1946; Photographs of objects used in the book. Label notes that "much of the material in the book was made in the Veterans' Art Center - World War II": mounted b/w prints removed from post album (Box 41, Folder VII.6)
  - [How to Make Modern Jewelry] (1 of 4), [1946]; Photographs of objects, and students working: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 41, Folder VII.7)
  - [How to Make Modern Jewelry] (2 of 4), [1946]; Photographs of objects, and students working: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 41, Folder VII.8)
  - [How to Make Modern Jewelry] (3 of 4), [1946]; Photographs of objects, and students working: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 42, Folder VII.9)
  - [How to Make Modern Jewelry] (4 of 4), [1946]; Photographs of objects, and students working: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 42, Folder VII.10)
  - How to Make Pottery and Ceramic Sculpture(1 of 2), 1946; Photographs from the pamphlet: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 42, Folder VII.11)
  - How to Make Pottery and Ceramic Sculpture(2 of 2), 1946; Photographs from the pamphlet: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 42, Folder VII.12)
  - How to Make Objects of Wood(1 of 4), Spring 1947; Photographs from "War Veterans Art Center World War II woodworking pamphlet": mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 42, Folder VII.13)
  - How to Make Objects of Wood(2 of 4), Spring 1947; Photographs from "War Veterans Art Center World War II woodworking pamphlet": mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 43, Folder VII.14)
  - How to Make Objects of Wood(3 of 4), Spring 1947; Photographs from "War Veterans Art Center World War II woodworking pamphlet": mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 43, Folder VII.15)
  - How to Make Objects of Wood(4 of 4), Spring 1947; Photographs from "War Veterans Art Center World War II woodworking pamphlet": mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 43, Folder VII.16)
  - "Culture and Education in World Order," by Herbert Read, 1948; Published for the Committee on Art Education by MoMA: three copies (Box 43, Folder VII.17)
  - How to Make Modern Jewelry, 1949; By Charles J. Martin, in collaboration with D'Amico (Box 43, Folder VII.18)
  - "Education Department books:How to Make Objects of Wood,How to Make Modern Jewelry", 1949, 1951; Captioned b/w prints with page numbers from book, removed from post album (Box 43, Folder VII.19)
  - Publications of MoMA, the People's Art Center, and joint publications with the Committee on Art Education, 1949-1960; Brochure from exhibition Timeless Aspects of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #393, November 16, 1948-January 23, 1949]; "Creative Art" (2 copies); "A study of the crafts in general education";Art and the intellect by Harold Taylor; “Clichés in Children's Paintings" by Jean D'Autilia;Art education and the creative process, by Archibald MacLeish (2 copies);Moral values and the experience of art, by Harold Taylor (Box 43, Folder VII.20)
  - Royalty statements and related correspondence, 1950-1955; Issued by MoMA as publisher of D'Amico's books (Box 43, Folder VII.21)
  - "Notes on a group meeting with Mr. Herbert Read on the subject of crafts", [after 1951]; Third statement to come out of a study of crafts education "undertaken in 1951 under the joint sponsorship of the American Craftsmen's Educational Council and the Committee on Art Education of the Museum of Modern Art": three copies (Box 44, Folder VII.22)
  - American Institute of Graphic Arts: Certificate of Excellence in printing for commerce, 1952; Awarded to D'Amico for Creative Art for Children, Young People, Adults, Schools (Box 71, Folder VII.23*)
  - Art for the Family, 1952-1953; Photographs of objects made by children and adults: b/w prints (Box 44, Folder VII.24)
  - Art for the Family, 1952-1953; B/w prints, including some not used in the publication (Box 44, Folder VII.25)
  - Art for the Family(1 of 3), [1954]; Captioned photographs for the book, identified by page number: b/w prints removed from post album (Box 44, Folder VII.26)
  - Art for the Family(2 of 3), [1954]; Captioned photographs for the book, identified by page number: b/w prints removed from post album (Box 44, Folder VII.27)
  - Art for the Family(3 of 3), [1954]; Captioned photographs for the book, identified by page number: b/w prints removed from post album (Box 44, Folder VII.28)
  - Art for the Family, first edition, 1954; Copy inscribed by D'Amico (Box 44, Folder VII.29)
  - Art of the Young Child, book and exhibition, 1956, 1960; Includes installation views from Art of the Young Child[MoMA Exh. #593, December 6, 1955-January 15, 1956]: b/w prints, negatives (Box 44, Folder VII.30)
  - Educational publications, [1960s]; Typed list of publications by Department of Education staff members (Box 44, Folder VII.31)
  - Images collected for publication, [1960s]; Photographic prints from various eras, possibly collected for use in Art for the Family or Experiments in Creative Art Teaching (Box 44, Folder VII.32)
  - Assemblage works, [1960s]; B/w photographs; possibly considered for publication in Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action (Box 44, Folder VII.33)
  - Art of the Young Child, book, 1960; Three copies (Box 44, Folder VII.34)
  - "The Museum of Modern Art as an Educational Institution", July 1, 1960; Publication issued as part of the Museum's 30th anniversary events; includes summary of MoMA's educational activities from 1929 to 1960 (Box 45, Folder VII.35)
  - The Cinema of Orson Welles, by Peter Bogdanovich, 1961; A publication of MoMA's Film Library (Box 45, Folder VII.36)
  - Brochure "The Museum of Modern Art and its program of international exchange in the arts", 1961 (Box 45, Folder VII.37)
  - Experiments in Creative Art Teaching, 1963; Two copies (Box 45, Folder VII.38)
  - Art as the Measure of Man, 1964; Essays by Stoddard, Edman, and Bettelheim: published by MoMA, edited by D'Amico (Box 45, Folder VII.39)
  - Art for the Family, second edition, 1966; Four copies (Box 45, Folder VII.40)
  - MoMA annual reports, 1966-1967, 1969-1970 (Box 45, Folder VII.41)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1966; Images of children at work that may have been considered for use in the book: color slides (Box 45, Folder VII.42)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1966-1972; Photographs of and by Arlette Buchman, presumably for use in the book: b/w prints, color slides (Box 45, Folder VII.43)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1966, 1973; Flyer, order form, correspondence (Box 45, Folder VII.44)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, [1972]; Typed table of contents, hand-edited publishing agreement with D'Amico (Box 45, Folder VII.45)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(1 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 45, Folder VII.46)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(2 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 45, Folder VII.47)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(3 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 45, Folder VII.48)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(4 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 45, Folder VII.49)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(5 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 46, Folder VII.50)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(6 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 46, Folder VII.51)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(7 of 7), 1972; Production photographs: b/w prints with notes re: enlargement for publication, some mounted (Box 46, Folder VII.52)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(1 of 5), 1972; Duplicate photographs: b/w prints (Box 46, Folder VII.53)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(2 of 5), 1972; Duplicate photographs: b/w prints (Box 46, Folder VII.54)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(3 of 5), 1972; Duplicate photographs: b/w prints (Box 46, Folder VII.55)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(4 of 5), 1972; Duplicate photographs: b/w prints (Box 46, Folder VII.56)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action(5 of 5), 1972; Duplicate photographs: b/w prints (Box 46, Folder VII.57)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1972; "Reproductions used for motivations"; includes photographs of children at work, and art by artists in MoMA's collection: b/w prints and contact sheet, color prints and transparencies (Box 46, Folder VII.58)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1972; Copy negatives (Box 46, Folder VII.59)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, 1972; Identified by book chapter, with caption and artist information: color transparencies (Box 47, Folder VII.60)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, [1972]; Images originally labeled "Photographs by Kathryn Abbe Children at Barge" that may have been considered for use in the book: color slides (Box 47, Folder VII.61)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, [1972]; Production photographs, some labeled for layout and size: b/w prints (Box 47, Folder VII.62)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, [1972]; 8 rolls exposed negatives: some images were used in the publication.; NOTE: Because of their fragile physical condition, these items are not available for viewing. (Box 48, Folder VII.63)
  - Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action, [1972]; Promotional brochure, order form, three photocopies of chapter XI, section on machine assemblage (Box 47, Folder VII.64)
  - "New Dimensions in Art Education, a book on collage and construction integrated with painting and other media", [1972]; 5" audio reel; possibly related to the publication Assemblage: A New Dimension in Creative Teaching in Action; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 47, Folder VII.65)
- Series VIII. Professional Involvement, 1935-1980, 1985, 1996 (bulk 1948-1968)
  The series documents D'Amico's work in education apart from MoMA, including his initial survey, funded by the Rockefeller Foundation, that led to the establishment of the Educational Project at MoMA; consultation with other educational institutions; and his long involvement with the National Committee on Art Education, including audio tapes of some of the organization's conference sessions held at MoMA and elsewhere.
  Subseries VIII.A. Education General,1935-1980, 1985, 1996
  Subseries VIII.B. Education-Related Correspondence,1947-1969
  Subseries VIII.C. National Committee on Art Education,1943-1969
  - Subseries VIII.A. Education General, 1935-1980, 1985, 1996
    - "Art in American schools": reports on schools visited (1 of 3), 1935; Survey funded by the Rockefeller Foundation: pages disbound from album (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.1)
    - "Art in American schools": reports on schools visited (2 of 3), 1935; Survey funded by the Rockefeller Foundation: pages disbound from album (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.2)
    - "Art in American schools": reports on schools visited (3 of 3), 1935; Survey funded by the Rockefeller Foundation: pages disbound from album (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.3)
    - “The visual arts in secondary education” (1 of 3), 1937; Report to Commission on the Secondary School Curriculum (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.4)
    - “The visual arts in secondary education” (2 of 3), 1937; Report to Commission on the Secondary School Curriculum (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.5)
    - “The visual arts in secondary education” (3 of 3), 1937; Report to Commission on the Secondary School Curriculum (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.6)
    - School Art League, Boys Club of New York, St. Luke's School, [1940s-1950s]; Photographs of art programs at MoMA and other New York City institutions: b/w prints (Box 47, Folder VIII.A.7)
    - Art Bibliography, 1941, 1947; Prepared by staff members of the Art Department, Teachers College (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.8)
    - Everson Trust, 1946-1949; Correspondence; includes carbon of D'Amico's report and recommendations to the Everson Fund trustee (First Trust & Deposit Co., Syracuse, NY) re: establishment of a memorial art museum in honor of Helen Everson (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.9)
    - Everson Trust, August 28, 1948; Mimeographed document summarizing provisions of Helen Everson's will and recommendations re: establishment of memorial art museum in her honor (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.10)
    - Statements, 1955-1957; Payment for service by D'Amico on professional panels for The New York Times, New York University (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.11)
    - “The Creative Element in Human Experience,” by Harold Taylor, November 11, 1960; Address to the Ohio Art Education Association (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.12)
    - Charles Cook memorial publication, August 1960-February 1962; Correspondence re: 8/27/1960 death of Charles Cook, who was a noted art educator, colleague of D'Amico's at Fieldston School, and previous executive director of University Settlement; includes letter D'Amico-Martin Fredericks (2/16/1962) proposing naming the Art Barge lounge in Cook’s honor (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.13)
    - Charles Cook memorial publication, October 1960, undated; Photographs, clipping; writings and conference presentations by Cook (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.14)
    - Charles Cook memorial publication, 1962; Contributed chapters, correspondence (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.15)
    - List of art reproductions, and preferences of children by age, August 1961; Includes correspondence of MoMA art teacher Jane Cooper Bland (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.16)
    - Chicago art exams (1 of 3), 1963, undated; Correspondence; typed, handwritten, and carbons of examination questions for high school art teachers (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.17)
    - Chicago art exams (2 of 3), 1963, undated; Correspondence; typed and carbons of examination questions for high school art teachers (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.18)
    - Chicago art exams (3 of 3), [1963]; Tabulated examination results (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.19)
    - Correspondence received, 1963, 1965, 1966, undated; From professional colleagues, including reactions to published articles by D'Amico (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.20)
    - Marshallton Educational Center, Marshallton, DE, December 3, 1964; Supporting information for planned art center including blueprint, outline specifications from local architecture firm, thesis on impact of the physical environment on children's art work, with transmittal note to D'Amico (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.21)
    - Art Educators Association of the City of New York Honor, 1965-1966; Photographs of presentation of Citation of Honor to Hon. Thomas Hoving: b/w prints (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.22)
    - “Victor D’Amico”, March 1966; 7" audio reel: audio conference D'Amico held with Red Creek Central School; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.23)
    - New York University art seminars, March, September, October 1967; Clippings used as visual motivations; correspondence with New York University education professors Howard Conant and Prabha Sahasrabudhe (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.24)
    - Education-related resources, January 1969, undated; Includes bibliography of art teaching resources, Report on the Art Department of Michigan State University, English Catholic High School Course (Box 49, Folder VIII.A.25)
    - “About Art: Kuniyoshi, Epstein Dali”; “Ohio save and copy”, [1970s]; Three otherwise unidentified standard audio cassettes (Box 50, Folder VIII.A.26)
    - Art Education Workshop, New York University, August 1970; Hand-written notes by D'Amico, blank evaluation forms (Box 50, Folder VIII.A.27)
    - New York University discussion, [August 1970]; 5" audio reel, unboxed; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 50, Folder VIII.A.28a)
    - New York University discussion, [August 1970]; 5" audio reel, unboxed; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 50, Folder VIII.A.28b)